I am very excited to be to be here today
to talk about some of our efforts in uh
developing training recipes for building
language models and particularly for
reasoning in language
models okay so let me start I want to
argue that AI uh is here today or we've
seen all this progress in AI because of
open scientific research and development
that is happening in this area and
because we had access to fully open
model however over time we've seen a lot
of research and development in this area
is getting closed off but what does that
mean now does it mean that now we are
done with scientific language modeling
research and Innovation I would argue no
we need still to do a lot of research to
understand the science of language
models to improve them and also build
their next generation
also we need to make a lot of advances
to push language models Beyond uh
language right like in science domains
language modeled for health uh and move
it Beyond text also we need to mitigate
their biases and risk use these language
models in real world uh obviously work
on LM agents improve their planning
reasoning test time scaling and also
make them suitable for deployment and
build efficient model
so with that I want to argue to
facilitate Innovation and also
accelerate the science of language
models we need these models to be fully
open we want them to be transparent we
have access to their data we want them
to be accessible and reproducible by
researchers and
developers so at udab and ai2 this is
our Focus we like to build an ecosystem
such that we can build language models
from at different stages from
pre-training to posttraining to
mid-training and also building agents in
particular uh my team is leading to
efforts called open language model uh
MMO and Tulu which is our open post
training
recipes I also want to highlight that
this fully open ecosystem is only one
piece of puzzle in this landscape of AI
these days okay so with this with this
project MMO we like to develop study an
advanced language model we want all our
efforts to be fully open documented and
reproducible and with this we like to
empower the AI community and also uh
inform the public about how AI works and
so on okay so in this talk I'm gonna uh
talk about three efforts that we've done
to improve mostly reasoning in language
models and these three directions are
mostly orthogonal and I'm going to talk
about pre-training post training and
inference time inference uh test time
inference and many of my slides are from
my amazing students uh and team members
who have worked on these
projects okay so in the past year or so
we have released uh and launched a bunch
of models and toolkits uh that we
encourage all of you to work and improve
event in pre-training we have released
almost one and two our mixture of expert
version and also our full pre-training
data during for posttraining we have
developed our training recipe on top of
many open weight models such as a llama
uh Quin and so on and also we've applied
that to our uh fully open language model
Almo and also we have all the toolkit
data and so on publicly available and
most recently we' continued working on
test time scaling which we have released
a swan open scholar and self frag which
I'm going to very briefly talk about
those three as well okay so just a quick
snapshot of where results are standing
is in our latest release of allm two
which we have released almost at 7
billion parameter and 13 billion
parameter scale the base model at the
end of pre-training it is on par and
some data sets better a little bit worse
on some data set but on average on par
with llama 3 and Quin 2.5 same as
13B importantly we have used less number
of training tokens and we argue thato
two is on this perto optimal curve
compared to many other kind of open
weight models uh like quen uh uh Quin
2.5 llama 3.1 and so on so this curve
shows the approximate uh shows the
average performance versus the
approximate uh pre-training flops and as
you see those are kind of those two
stars show where to
stands um a a snapshot of our uh post
training efforts so uh most recently we
have developed our post trining recipe
on top of the largest open weight model
which was llama
405b uh and I'm going to talk about how
this process is being done in this talk
and I uh I can show you that Tulu 3
405b now is on par or better than deeps
V3 and almost on par with GPT 40 which
is which is very impressive uh uh
showing that now now we are getting
really good result compared to even
proprietary models okay so with that I
first want to start with post training
because a lot of our efforts on how to
make these models able to reason starts
from post training uh or happens during
the post training uh and I kind of talk
will talk about how we develop Tulu Al
learn this process okay so how do we
build a modern large language model so
it is roughly going these two stages
pre-training and
post-training in Pre training the models
are trained with predicting the next uh
the next token where data usually comes
from long large and large uh scale data
mostly from the web okay but the model
that comes out of this stage is not
ready to be used for a lot of
applications it is not safe it's
probably not able to follow human
instructions and uh it's not that good
at reasoning
when post training happens now models
can do a lot of things it can chat it
follows instructions you can integrated
with tool use it's able to reason uh
it's able to tell you when it is harmful
when it doesn't kind of uh follow the
instruction and so on okay so we do Post
training to align with human preferences
you've seen it in like when for example
use chat GPT which of these two
responses you prefer and like we collect
this type of data to say which of these
outcomes are more align with humans
in uh we do post trainining to be able
to follow to do tool use searching code
execution and so on and also we do a lot
in post training for models to be able
to reason for example in this case we
want to teach the model how to kind of
solve this arithmetic word
problem okay so how does it work uh
following many standard language
modeling or machine learning uh
pipelines it requires these these pieces
data the data that need we need to train
on a training kind of architecture and
neural network which in almost all cases
it's a Transformer based architecture
and a very thorough evaluation Loop to
tell us where we are improving where
things are not going so well okay and
I'm going to talk about these are the
three integral part parts in building a
very modern successful language model
data models and algorithms and during
this talk I'm going to talk about what
type of data is important and what type
of algorithms are useful for which type
of data okay so data plays a really
important role in building these
post-rain models and like pre-trained
model it comes from different sources in
many different forms and they are
targeting diverse capabilities right so
for example we need data to be able to
solve math word problems we need data to
build agents we need data to kind of
tell the model when it is not safe to
response to a
query but we need to design and use
different algorithms on deciding when to
use the right data and how which of
these algorithms are useful when okay so
uh this was our effort throughout this
Tulu project which is started from
2023 uh and now we have an open
reproducible and state-of-the-art
post-training recipe and we can apply it
on many different open weight models
okay in the first version which we
worked on this on June
2023 we pretty much only showed what is
the best recipe to develop supervised
fine-tuning data or instruction data I'm
going to dig into all these a little bit
deeper uh in the next slides in the
second version we showed that how we
bring and digest a preference
data um and then finally we started
doing very systematic study on what are
the best algorithms to use these type of
preference tuning data and at the end of
these stages we managed to show that uh
with only open-source models we can be
as good as chat GPT even upsetting GPT
for finally in um in the at the end of
last year in November we we released
Tulu 3 which pretty much put all our
efforts together such that we develop
Tulu 3 okay and then we applied the same
recipe onmo showing that the fully open
training recipe also works okay so what
is this training recipe so it starts
from a base model and we are following
three important steps in instruction
tuning preference tuning and uh our new
novel method we call it reinforcement
learning with verifiable rewards okay
and sometimes we have to do a bunch of
kind of back and forth between these
stages and I'm going to talk about how
this works okay so let's first start
getting the ingredients to start with
which is data okay so in order to do a
successful post training we first need
to establish meaningful evaluation
for targeted skills for example for Tulu
three these were our goal we want to
have General chat capabilities we want
our model to be able to do to be good at
knowledge recall math and reasoning
coding um safety and non-compliance
multilingual and also very precisely uh
follow instructions even when it kind of
show some
constraints okay so we developed all
these kind of evaluations benchmarks
like we decided what type of evaluation
data sets sometimes we also had to
create the data sets ourself on how to
evaluate if our model has acquired good
uh capabilities in all of these
categories that I just talked about okay
and we also followed really good old
machine learning techniques which we set
some of these data sets for development
and then kept some as hidden and we just
evaluated at the end of uh when all our
training was done okay so given our
emphasis on these capabilities we
started collecting prompts like kind of
queries and instructions that we think
our model should be able to answer okay
we checked for licenses are they kind of
uh collected uh with a user consent uh
how how the licensing work and then make
sure that we decontaminate them with the
evaluation sets that we are evaluating
on this is very important because we've
noticed in the literature people show
some really good data sets getting
really good results on certain
benchmarks but uh the decontamination
wasn't done carefully because we are
talking about very complex instances uh
and it's very easy for some of the test
sets to be de to be contaminated so we
in our open instruct toolkit we have a
code available for all these cases and
it's really useful to follow this
okay so now that we have the ingredients
we want to go through the first step
which is instruction tuning or sometimes
called supervised fine tuning what does
that mean it basically is a very simple
step it takes a lot of these prompts and
completions and then fine tune a
pre-train language model to be able to
follow these instructions right so for
example we can have queries like answer
these questions one by one summarize
this St like many of these type of
questions and then the the final answers
okay but how do we curate this data how
do we Source this data we can have and
Source this data through human
annotation which obviously it is costly
it is time consuming and also it has
high variance right now sometimes
particularly in tasks like reasoning we
are dealing with complex annotations and
it might not be well suited for kind of
General
annotators another approach where we
which we introduced in our 2023 self-
instruct paper was to synthetically
generate these data with kind of
self-loop or self-instruction loop with
another language model okay so kind of
synthetic data
generation and obviously it is good it's
really good in a lot of cases but it's
going to be noisy as well okay and it is
biased to the language model that we are
generating this data from okay and most
recently we've discovered the optimal
solution is combining both of them which
we kind of uh build a hybrid collection
of data coming from Human annotation and
also from synthetically generated by
other uh language models okay so data
curation has been uh kind of received
well within the open source Community uh
we had some earlier work in 2022 on we
called it natural instructions and
Supernatural instructions where we only
focused on kind of NLP relevant task
where we were looking at tasks like
question answering summarization
translation and so on then we developed
a self- instruct framework where we
generate data synthetically this has
picked up really well within the
community many kind of an next efforts
have been uh introduced within the
community to generate more and more
synthetic data set like alpaca wuna and
so on and so forth uh we Al have a very
good collection of data sets that are
mostly focused on kind of uh short form
uh question answering type test like
flan V1 and so on so so I'm just listing
a few of these data sets here uh for the
full set please check out Tulu 3 paper
we listed a lot of publicly available
data sets either manually curated expert
curated or synthetically generated by
the community and we kind of combine a
lot of them use the ones that we saw
most signal out of them in our to build
our final sfd
mix okay so now we have looked at uh all
these kind of data that are available
and now we are doing these two repeated
parallelizable tracks where we collect
this data and now we want to mix them
such that we get high accuracy in the
capabilities that we care about this
requires substantial effort why because
for example if I add a lot of data about
por generation probably my math
reasoning capabilities drop if I add a
lot of data on math reasoning probably I
would lose this kind of creative task
like like poem generation right so it's
it's a pretty challenging task to keep a
good balance of all these data such that
we are getting high accur accuracy
across the board okay so we are
exploring and also in the community
people are exploring many different ways
of this data mixing including um manual
kind of empirical analysis uh automated
mixing um and I think the the the
literature is evolving and there are a
lot of active research going on in this
area
okay so let me show you some of our
efforts in how we how we did this data
mixing in our Tulu one which was kind of
very simple there were not much data
available in
2023 uh such that we kind of start doing
all these combination so first we
combined all available open data sets
that were uh available back then okay
and I'm I'm listing them and the left
and some of them are created by humans
uh general public or uh experts and then
some are synthesized with some of the
most successful language models back
there okay then similar to what I just
described we started kind of build
looking at uh evaluation sets or data
sets targeted to evaluate certain
capabilities for example this is the
outcome of our fine-tuning when we were
evaluating on kind of chat Ty evaluation
sets Okay and here are how the results
compare the red ones mean like the
results are not that good and then the
blue ones show okay successful results
um like as you see here that GPT for
alpaca shows good high results uh on
chat type evaluation share GPT also
showing good uh good results on chat
evaluation so we did that across many
different kind of verticals knowledge
reasoning coding multilinguality and
safety and some some of these results
are quite exciting like for example when
we train with Chain of Thought data we
see higher numbers on uh reasoning type
evaluation
sets Okay so now the question is how do
we combine them how do how do we take
the best of all all of these RS because
as you saw uh this data actually let me
go back here this data like uh uh share
GPT or uh self instruct uh or like I was
I would say open Assistant one that is
good in chat they are not that good in
knowledge or reasoning type test right
so it is important to kind of get the
best of all these words so we tried to
look at the uh the data sets that show
kind of high numbers across one of these
verticals and started combining them and
as a result we have a human plus
synthetic type
data okay I want to highlight that we
saw really good results with Shar GPT
early on but we later dropped this data
because Li since and the way the data
was collected was not that good so so we
dropped this data in our next
versions okay now with the emphasis on
reasoning I want to dig a little bit
deeper on what type of data particularly
is useful for
reason okay why why is this challenging
let me give you a math example we want
to solve this problem the question is uh
you can read this here A store has buy
to get one free deal on shirts each
shirt cost $25 if Sarah wants to buy
seven shirts how much will she spend
okay so one quick thing could be okay I
have this problem the the final answer
is $125 it's pretty easy to come up with
that number okay however if I just fune
a model with this kind of input output
setting probably I won't get that that
that much out of this training instance
okay so we all observe in the community
that it's really better if we start
integrating and using this type of Chain
of Thought output where we say we're GNA
break this down into okay step one does
do this step two do this and then kind
of break this down as if you're are
explaining it to a child how to follow
this steps to come up with that final
number
$125 okay so why do to summarize why do
we think Chain of Thought data is
helpful for reasoning it's helping the
model to handle complex multi-step
problems much easier it also starts kind
of revealing the model's reasoning
process also one thought is uh a lot of
these models during pre-training have
seen a lot of this type of Chain of
Thought data and then this kind of
starts to boost them up uh to boost this
capability up of saying okay remember
you knew how to think step by step bring
them up when you are looking at these
more complex math reasoning
problems also when we look at these type
of annotations uh this type of Chain of
Thought data makes it much easier to
spot errors in the logic and also uh it
kind of resembles how we are explaining
things uh to humans or how humans
thought process work okay these are all
very good points about why this type of
Chain of Thought data is
important however it's becoming more and
more challenging to observe and obtain
manual annotation uh for this type of
Chain of Thought data it is time
consuming it is very expensive right uh
and it often requires expert annotations
the example that I showed in the last
slide was quite easy but think of more
challenging math problems we need
experts to annotate those and obviously
it is difficult to escale and also it is
not diverse enough like it is very hard
to boost diversity with all these kind
of limitations that we have when we want
to collect this type of Chain of Thought
data okay so again our approach to
address this solution was hybrid data
curation where we look at data mixing
and also selecting from existing
resources we also did some very kind of
observed a very interesting uh paper
from the literature where they propose
to use different
personas to generate diverse data okay
so so I'm referring to this paper here
but the idea is uh we're gonna look at
different skills like for example math
coding precisely follow instruction but
then we devise different personas and
then we add the model to generate data
for those skills given the Persona that
it is kind of looking at this would uh
Ensure High diversity and enables us to
scale further what does that mean so we
kind of developed this uh this prompt we
say we want to create this data with
this specific Persona in mind like for
example we want to create a math problem
given that we are creating it for a
chemical kinetics researcher okay and
now the problem looks like this Dr Smith
a chemist is studying this and so on uh
or we say we want to solve this logical
reasoning problem again for that persona
for that chemical kinetics researcher we
tried a many different personas right uh
we designed these type of math problems
for uh for experts for children like
six-year-old CH children
uh or like a computer scientist a
musician right so you give many
different personal to the model and then
we ask the model to generate it
specifically designed for that
person with that we created more than
150k hard math problems uh and 50k grade
school math problem okay we created 35k
python coding and a precise instruction
followed uh then these were mostly for
generating prompts because these this
this was the point of boosting diversity
for the types of problems that we are
getting then we used a combination of
GPT 40 and Cloud Sonet to generate
stepbystep solutions for example for a
given math problem a coding or precise
instruction
follow okay so now let's look at the
result how successful and useful these
data are okay so let me walk through how
we read these
figures so in the in the in the figures
below you are seeing results on two data
sets math and gsmk which are do two
popular math uh data
sets then we each of these bars show a
combination of using our public data
sets like the data sets that are
available for example for math or
general purpose combined with this
Persona driven synthetic math problems
okay and we kind of varied the amount of
this Persona driven math data in our
experiments okay so the first bar the
the yellow bar just uses the general
public data and the last bar is kind of
does a 50 5050 between Persona driven
data and then General data okay and as
you see over time we see uh Improvement
mostly on the math uh on
gsmk we saw less Improvement and we we
think the reason is because gsmk are
simpar mat word problems like grer
School mat word problems and we think uh
the available public data set were
already good enough so that's why we
didn't uh gain much okay so uh to
summarize adding more Persona driven
data consistently improves ma
performance uh GS sm8 K improves but
it's much less uh and and kind of kind
of be kept a balance on how to use this
type of
personal okay so um we did another step
uh on to kind of filter the data how do
how do we do that for every word problem
or every kind of instance that was
generated uh
synthetically we actually went ahead and
asked gp4 to generate multiple reasoning
paths and then we basically did
self-consistency so in in in one of the
classes earlier uh I think this this
semester or last semester you learned
about self-consistent and here is what
we used and then we basically See Saw
which one has majority vote and kept
those reasoning pads that gave us that
kind of better answer so through this we
managed to filter a lot of data um
almost 40% of the data and now we are
seeing that using only 60% of the data
we are getting similar performance on
math right this new pink is the is the
filtered kind of process data which is
almost on par I would say this is just
kind of error bar on how different they
are from the original mix H and we saw
significant more significant boost on
the gsmk kind of highlighting that with
this better filter data uh we are
getting higher accuracy on gsmk so uh at
the end of the day now we are able to
use uh this 60% of the data and we are
getting good performance from this
synthetically generated
data okay so there are many other
approaches uh in the in the research
Community to generate Chain of Thought
data one is obviously manual human
annotation as I mentioned this is great
this is very accurate but we can pretty
much have a limited scale and sometimes
it is hard to increase diversity in the
reasoning scale in the reasoning style
and there are methods that they convert
match problems into python code and then
generate solutions that way this is
great because it guarantees correctness
through execution um it is the only
issue is it's a little bit less natural
uh like natural language reasoning the
same way that you are explaining it to a
child so somewhat less intuitive but
it's still very interesting and uh it it
works really well uh and also this type
of self generated Chain of Thought uh
which is scalable to many problems uh
the quality of the model really depends
on the base model and we kind of did a
combination of uh all of these methods
okay so putting all these the uh all
these together so I uh talked a lot
about how we created and curated these
synthetic data for Math and reasoning
then we put all of these together and
built our data mix for supervised fine
tuni and this is the outcome uh which is
the combination of human and synthetic
data and we finally build Tulu
sft so uh let's discuss a little bit of
results
uh so this table has a lot of numbers
but I want to show kind of some of the
ablations we've done um The Columns show
many different data sets that we
evaluated on uh like MML tqa pop QA and
and they are all kind of evaluating some
of those poor skills that we cared about
and this is our final results on The
Final sfd Mix that we discovered uh and
these are some of the ablations like for
example if we move wild chat which is
kind of our data mix to approach General
chat capabilities uh our average will
get into
58.9 um with probably the biggest drop
on as you see here alpaca eval on chat
evaluations uh or without the Persona
data we get to
58.6 uh where we saw drops on for
example math and so on okay or or math
dat if we remove that we see a really
significant drop uh on this type of math
evaluation uh another thing that we were
we were very careful was we want to make
sure our model is safe so we added
safety data but at the same time we want
to make sure that it doesn't drop uh the
capabilities the general capabilities of
the model and this is what we've observe
that adding safety data doesn't hurt
General capabilities of the model um
this is also comparing the Tulu sft data
with the other data sets that were
available in the community like Mammoth
data or rlf these were some of the most
popular data sets that exist in the
community uh and this is like the gains
that we are having um like 46 56 and
these were our earlier like Tulu 2 sfd
is like our earliest data mix in our
earlier versions so in in overall I will
argue that uh this is a really good as
FD Mix A Lot More can be done here uh
and it's really good if like people in
the open source Community also start
improving this data
mix okay so Step One is done we took our
base model and then uh did supervised
fine tuning with a very carefully
curated data mix okay next step is
preference tuning where it works with
the reward model okay let's see what
happens here so at the preference fine
tuning stage um I think Jason also
talked about this is the goal is we want
to align to human preferences for
example we have this query we say write
a high cou about AI um uh it it talks
about the the model comes and output
something we want to give thumbs up
thumbs down if the output seems good or
back okay so in but but in practice what
we've observed the role of preference
finetuning is to show a very strong
training signal to make a style uh to to
have a better style of chats and it
shows really higher improvements on chat
type
evaluation it also keeps improving the
basic capabilities that we were
targeting uh but in general we saw lower
abolute magnitude of improvement for
like very kind of for for for example
math type capabilities
okay um
so let's dig a little bit deeper how the
preference data looks like so we have
this prompt let's say explain the moon
landing to a six-year-old in a few
sentences we want our model to generate
two responses okay and then the
preference instant tells us one response
is better than the other one right and
it can be annotated by humans saying
that this response to me seems much more
suitable for a six-year
old uh most recently people look at this
called RL aif where instead of humans we
can have another AI model let's say GPT
40 Cloud on it on so uh to evaluate
which of these responses are better for
a six-year-old
and then the algorithm to kind of update
that at some level sometimes is called
rla okay so but this is the nature of
data why does this data play an
important role in kind of building and
and and post training stages is in a lot
of cases we are dealing with open-ended
generations and kind of had coming up
with some absolute numbers to say oh
okay this response is good is hard
however it's much easier to deal with
comparison to say this response is
generally better than the other one so
the task of annotation has become much
easier okay but then we cannot use the
same supervised fine-tuning algorithm to
deal with this type of preference data
now let me unpack r lhf or reinforcement
learning with human feedback how do we
integrate and use this type of
preference data
okay so uh we will use reinforcement
learning how does it work this is the
most generic form okay the idea is this
is kind of the most generic definition
of RL the idea is for a given policy
which is generate the next token we
generate this next token we interact
with an environment up uh we get some
reward from the environment if that
generated token was good or bad and then
update this state of the world in
rhf the state is getting updated from
the prompts that are getting fed into
the
policy the action uh is updating and
finding what responses are and then the
environment is actually a reward model
where it tells us how good uh a model uh
like kind of tries to model the
preference says that this response is
generally preferred over the other one
okay so this is kind of how rlf
works this reference data will fit into
a reward model where reward model is
actually a neural network that is a
trained to tell us for a given prompt
which response is better okay how do we
optimize this complex
situation uh through po training let's
dig a little bit deeper the idea is we
want to maximize the reward kind of we
want to get the maximal reward as
possible okay such that we want to
constrain the model to stay as close as
possible to the base language model
right like we want the policy to don't
go that far from the originally trained
model okay so this is a this is
establishing a very important balance
between make sure you are aligned with
those preference es that are provided to
you however don't go too far from the
original model that you have in mind
okay now in the last year or so many
different variants are introduced on how
to optimize that objective okay so uh in
the most uh in in in last year we had
this paper called direct preference
optimization or DPO where the idea is
what if we just use gradient sent on
this equation okay let's kind of ignore
all that like now we have this reward
model and then uh and then we we want to
optimize for that reward let's directly
optimize uh for these human preferences
and then kind of model it as a as a
ranking model
okay so how does the DPO training work
it it's like this where we kind of a
remove a lot of these details here and
we directly go from the preference data
into into policy and then kind of given
that reference model we want to see how
close uh this preference data is to the
the policy so many new variants of DP
also introduced so here I'm summarizing
them this is the PO the original
formulation here is the direct
preference optimization which directly
optimizes the policy given the
preference data I would I would always
say think of it as kind of some sort of
ranking uh objective
uh and then the newer variance like simp
which even makes it more simplified
where it doesn't even use a preference
uh a reference model uh another variant
uh like length normalized DPO which
normalizes the same leg likelihood uh
but kind of make it normalize for the
legs okay so in our uh this work uh we
started actually uh digging deeper into
all these algorithms that exist okay
particularly if we looked at comparing
between DPO and po okay so they they are
all different right they they are
getting different types of parameters
they have different implementation
complexity memory usage throughput and
so on just to give you a very brief idea
uh in general we saw po performs better
than DPO in almost all cases however it
is much more complicated to implement
and make it work particularly for larger
models why because at P for po we need
to have two models running like we we
have the reward model as a neural
network and also the policy model which
is kind of the the actual language model
that generates token okay so so it
really depends on uh the the developers
preference on which constraints they
have okay so let let me dig a little bit
deeper and tell you what things we abled
to figure out um which model to use okay
for DPO remember we had preference data
and policy model for po we have all
these components preference data the
type of reward model and the neural
network that we have here we have the
generations the prompts and the policy
model okay so um I'm kind of showing the
final results I'm not going going into a
lot of details but here are the results
let's say this is the average
performance on a lot of tasks that we've
looked at this is the initial sfd
result when we do DPO with some sort of
weaker preference tuning uh we saw 2%
boost okay when we do a lot of ablations
and very careful curation of preference
data we saw significant boost like look
at this we go from 56 to 61 just with
better data selection data curation here
then we replace DPO with po we saw now
we just just use the exact same data we
just replace the algorithm DPO with p
and we saw one point boost here then we
thought okay now this is very promising
PO is great let's now think of a big
reward model because remember reward
model plays this environment role and we
kind of try to
uh make our model as close as possible
to this kind of preference data okay
when we started using a bigger reward
model we didn't saw that much
improvement like less than like about
half a point
Improvement uh and then finally when we
started mixing prompts of uh what type
of specific design prompts for some task
on average we didn't see much game okay
however I want to highlight that that uh
this this final step on average didn't
show us a lot of improvement but very
interestingly when we only focused on
reasoning particularly
gsmk uh when we started bringing up
prompts that are very useful like uh for
for improving the reasoning capabilities
we saw significant boosts here that here
we learn when we introduce prompts that
are domain specific for some of those
capabilities is they play a really
important role okay so if you look at
this whole thing uh this was the choice
of algorithm this was the choice of data
algorithm model data so so again we saw
a really big boost on data okay so
takeways from this the most important
factor in building a really good
preference tuning algorithm uh for us
was high quality data po works better
than DPO but DPO is much cheaper to
experiment with and kind of do ablations
on data uh and it's kind of more
practical for development scaling RM
reward models uh help but not
significantly using end domain prompts
yield performance gains particularly for
domains like
reasoning okay so now we put all of
those together when we want to build two
three okay so from our last study we
learned prompt selection is really
important uh so we looked at many
different combinations on how to curate
data and this was kind of our best mix
we want to use some of the prompts that
we already used in sfd we thought this
is really good to maintain accuracy and
performance uh we also brought some
prompts some new prompts that we hadn't
seen during sft and then we started br
ining in out of domain prompts uh for
example from domains that we did not
study in uh
sft okay so we then did a lot of
response generation from all these
models okay so we had some weaker models
like 7B models uh llama 7B for example
almost 7B all the way to very kind of a
strong models like GPT 40 because we
want to look at the preferences to see
which of these outputs are more
preferable importantly we brought on
policy data remember we want to improve
our Tulu 3 sft right this is the model
this is the policy model that we want to
improve upon so we made sure to bring
some of these data points uh and and
these Tulu three completions such that
we can say this outcome is preferred
over something uh worse or
we need to get to something better which
is for example the outcome of gp4 so we
also show that it is important to use
this on policy
data okay um then we did particularly RL
aif where we asked GPT 40 to tell us
which of these completions are better
and we ask it to measure across these
four categories helpfulness instruction
following how accurately it could follow
instructions how truthful and how honest
these responses are uh and then we
binarize them according to like and and
then said which is chosen which is
rejected to optimize the algorithm for
optimization we did a DPO Po and C again
similarly we didn't see much gains from
Po and for Simplicity we stick with DP
for this okay so here are these bottom
figures show some of our relations uh so
actually let's look at the the the most
the right hand one which is what llm as
judge we used for kind of telling us
which is uh preferred which is uh
rejected uh and we looked at many
different kind of uh highly capable
models like GPT
40 uh llama 405 and so on and we saw um
a little bit better results on GPT 40
and that's what we stick with
this middle uh uh figure evaluates the
off policy versus on policy
preferences um and as you see this is
the initial sft uh with off policy we
got to 60 adding on policy uh only with
on policy we get 60.7 and then combining
all of them uh we got the best
numbers uh here uh we also checked if it
is in if it is useful to bring in new
out of domain prompts or we just reuse
some of the prompts that we had from the
initial sft and as you see again uh
bringing new new prompts also improves
results okay so what happened up to here
uh we did all our instruction tuning
supervised fine tuning we did our
preference tuning and now I want to talk
about our third step which we introduced
uh as part of our tool BL three effort
reinforcement learning with verifiable
reward
okay so let's look at these
curves at the end
of uh DPO or preference tuning stage I'm
going to show you these three figures
okay so this is training steps on the on
the xais and on the y axis we are
looking looking at evaluation
performance and as you see over time for
example in the alpaca
Eva um we see the improvements are
almost getting plat out okay for eal
which is how we do instruction following
interestingly we see when we increase
the training steps in the for for our DP
we see a little bit drop in
performance and for GSM K which is our
kind of uh proxy for reasoning we see
initial Improvement but then after some
time we started seeing overfitting and
then uh dropping performance okay so
particularly for these more complex task
like following instructions and doing
reasoning over time we see over
optimization is happening okay we which
is not good then we started thinking a
little bit about
this we are using this neural reward
model to tell us if uh if if kind of
some preferences are good or bad okay
this neural network tries to assign a
score to every instance now okay so it
tells us for this give this reward model
uh is trained to tell which is chosen
which is rejected but at the end of the
day for every completion it tells us
what is the score of this uh this
completion okay for example for
something like this for some prompt like
this it would give us this score of
10.5 okay uh if we change the input it
might give us another score okay also
there are studies in the literature that
this human feedback that okay this a is
preferred over B it's not the golden
standard of saying what is the outcome
uh what is a good reward the score for
this sentence for
example okay instead we thought for
tasks that are that we can verify their
correctness we can use a much much
simpler reward model okay or in fact we
can replace this reward model with
something rule based for example if my
query is what is 2 +
two we can easily say if the answer is
Gold return one otherwise return zero
okay if you were if it were only using
that neural reward model it might have
given us another score like uh 1,000 or
it might have given us something like I
don't know 5.5 right what is the
intuition what is the meaning behind
that score that the reward model is
giving us okay so that was where we
questioned this and then we said for
tasks that we can re re verify their
final outcome what if we just remove
that complex setup and use a much
simpler rule based model okay and this
is exactly what we did so let's look at
our RL setting the prompts come in the
state gets update the action uh are
generating next tokens and then this
reward model tells us what is the good
outcome uh or what is a good score
associated with this
generation however in problems like math
that we have ground truths
answer we can have this verification
function where the reward tells us one
if the final answer is correct zero
otherwise okay pretty much we had that
for gsmk which is one of our reasoning
eval math and also precise instruction
following let's imagine we are giving uh
the model a bunch of constraints like
make sure uh to start the sentence with
s
that or or to write a that has five
words right so you could verify if the
generated outcome follows these uh
constraints or not and then we can kind
of evaluate how uh how we can easily
verify how good the generated outcome
is okay so uh that that was pretty much
what we did we replaced the reward model
with the verification function uh and
this
uh the the Deep sick R1 model that
released earlier this year also is using
similar thing uh which I think they call
it a different name but a very very
similar
intuition okay to summarize uh this is
our setup uh we use gold final final
answer or verifiable constraints uh as
this kind of environment as a proxy for
environment this is good because for
this we don't need intermediate Chain of
Thought we just need the final answers
then we applied classical reinforcement
learning algorithm to optimize this and
here we used P for the optimization and
we tried it for three data set gsmk math
and if
verification um and kind of we show the
results roughly this is the number of
training instances that we have used uh
almost in the order of 100 110k okay um
we also evaluated on big bench heart
which is kind of also roughly reasoning
type task and then we found that this
flan data set could be a good proxy to
give us boost on
BPH um some of some of the verification
steps are very easy like math and
reasoning it's pretty much just this if
then else which is if prediction is
equal to this number say yes otherwise
as zero some of it for example for
constraints and constraint satisfaction
and verifications it's a little bit more
challenging because we want to see which
of these constraints are satisfied and
then we see which percentage of those
constraint are satisfied but in general
pretty similar pretty
easy so now let's look at the curves so
I'm just showing this whole graphs but
now let me go a little bit deeper here
okay so what does this uh curve uh tell
us so on the x axis we see the training
steps and then on the Y AIS we show the
uh gsmk the math resen in
capability this dashed green line is the
outcome of the supervised fine-tuning
model the pink one is the outcome of the
DPO model okay so we applied uh rvr at
two
stages just to see if it makes
Improvement both at the end of
supervised fine tuning and also at the
end of DPO so what do we see this is
interesting uh curves show results are
going up we don't see that much over
parameter optimization here the gains on
top of sfd is much higher but the
biggest gain or like the the highest
number is achieved by when we apply it
on
DPO same things on math again at the
beginning we saw a little bit drop when
we have started with DPO but then again
start to see
improvements uh eal which is the
verification um on the constraint
optimization and like instruction
following when we start from sfd we saw
significant gains on DPO we saw less
gains we are still investigating on this
but we think the reason is we did not
have enough
data uh and interestingly when we use
plan data just to this was this was kind
of we did not finally include this in
our rvr mix but it was an interesting
observation just to see that uh doing
some reinforcement learning on FL um it
shows some improvements on some of the
reasoning tasks and it's worth exploring
this much more and we are doing it uh
just seeing what other types of
verifiable tasks out there such that we
can apply rvr on that okay okay um we
also appli the same recipe on MMO two uh
and we can kind of build upon this this
is this is actually a very interesting
setting um we stacked a bunch of
reinforcement learning steps one on top
of each other uh so here we started
doing a bunch of training and we kind of
cut it here this is the average score
and then again started a little bit
another step uh and then L kind of
stacked multiple rvrs and then did
multiple stages and over time we saw
even more improvements so so the the
pipeline is there we can do multiple
kind of uh tries with this to see if we
see uh bigger gains or
not okay I want to take a step back and
then talk about this this thing rvr is
not really new this is actually the
simplest way of to you of using RL with
real with the kind of data but why did
it work now we realize it's because and
now base model qualities have improved a
lot therefore RL can boost upon them
okay so what does this curve show me so
uh these are training steps this is the
accuracy and the green bar shows when we
do RL VR applying on gpt2 like the model
that existed long time ago which was
really bad so the the original number
like the base numbers are very low
unlike some of these reasoning tag
therefore reinforcement learning didn't
show
Improvement however because now our base
models are improving then applying rvr
on top of them show significant Gams and
this is very interesting to observe
because now model uh can start exploring
more and then exploited once it sees it
is following uh with with the with the
with the reward with this rule based
reward
okay so putting all these together uh we
scale this up from 7B to 70b to
405b uh and this is kind of our results
how it looks um on the pink portion you
see you see the results of the Tulu
model applied on llama 405b at uh the
the here are the results of sft DPO and
the final out of rvr uh again this is
the result comparing with deeps V3 and
GPT 40 the latest version on average uh
we are very close to GPT 40 better than
deeps V3 uh and it's and it's a very
exciting
area uh here are uh showing our results
on 8B and 70b models again comparing
with open weight models like quen
instruct and Lama instruct which like
better significantly and also at 7B 70b
where the smaller model are also
comparable to the kind of a smaller size
of gp4 or mini or Cloud
High okay um one other interesting
observation was RL VR works better at
the scale so here shows our Improvement
on math in two cases oh I didn't put
Legend um so here on on the left hand
side you see how much Improv we see on a
a 70b model and this is how much
improvement we saw on the right hand
side you see how much improvement we saw
at 405b and as you see here we started
from 60 went all the way to 67 like 7
point Improvement on math um whereas at
the uh 7 B 7 70b scale we go from 42 to
45 so it was interesting and kind of
align with our hypothesis that when we
have better base we can start seeing a
lot more Improvement during this rvr
step so we are exploring a lot and we
know the community is also exploring a
lot in this setup uh for example we have
changed our optimization algorithm from
po to grpo which I'm not going to go
into the details but now here are our
significant Improvement so to as a
reference to three four 5B has
67% and now um when we apply our recipe
on quen Matt model and then we apply
grpo now we are already getting 84.6 so
which is which is very exciting uh shows
a lot of progress can be done in this
domain okay so this is it so we these
are putting together all our Tulu three
recipe I first told talked about how we
got ingredients ready by collecting data
then we have different types of data at
different stages and we showed how we do
supervised fine tuning or instruction
fine tuning preference tuning which we
looked at the preference data and RL VR
which we just looked at this kind of uh
verification step and then putting all
these together we have to three uh here
is the the the model we also have the
demo of the model available in
playground. l.org where you can play
with this uh we are using this data to
kind of improve the next version of the
models uh and kind of improve
capabilities of two three also all our
code data uh and the the pipeline and
the framework are is ready
so whatever post-train model or adapted
model you want to build we argue it's
really important to bring in some of the
general cap capabilities to get better
model so I I would encourage you to use
that
data okay so um this is a fully open
post trining recipe we have applied it
to llama based model quen based model
and also on ouro models uh which shows
significant boosts uh on the on the kind
of uho Base models as well okay so with
that I would end out my discussions on
post training and I want to very briefly
talk about test time inference okay
which uh which is a very uh kind of
popular topic these days and a lot of
people are looking at how to bring in
test improvements particularly in
reasoning during test time
inference so I first uh want to talk
about this paper called a swan um which
is led by amazing Nicholas
manov uh and it is actually the very
minimal recipe for reasoning and test
time
scaling so let me tell you how it
works very similar to almost everything
else that is happening in language uh
models it relies on really carefully
curated data we call it s1k then we
apply test time scaling algorithm a very
simple one and this is the outcome this
one okay how do we curate data uh we
looked at a very large collection of uh
math logical reasoning probability
questions and so on like kind of more
higher level reasoning data it's even
beyond the Tulu three data uh where we
mostly looked at gr school and kind of
matth which was um highest school a
little bit college level math here we
are looking at much more complex like
even Olympiad uh or math competition
type data so we looked at all these
logic puzzles mat and we collected 59k
question but then we did a lot of
filtering here we filtered for Quality
we got into 52k Data we picked the ones
that were uh more difficult and then we
moved to uh 24K and then we emphasize
diversity and we kind of removed the
ones that they were very similar we
ended up having one K so spoiler alert
alert on our benchmarks using 59k data
and 1K data almost similar which is
which is very
interesting so once we collected these
prompts we started to distill reasoning
traces and answers um so for example
when we have a problem like this we gave
this problem which is among our like s1k
data and then we annotate annotated the
the kind of reasoning chains chain of
thoughts with Google thinking Gemini
model um also we made sure that this
data also includes some of the thinking
tokens like okay this this happens but
let me think more and so on so we use it
kind of Google thinking annotations and
most recently in S11 we replace Google
Gemini result uh annotations we deep
seek R1 results where it actually
improved the the final results which was
very interesting to
see okay so this is the final collection
of
data the data varies across all these
domains uh from geometry number Theory
uh to even very very smaller portion on
control theory astronomy and so on okay
so this is the data test time scaling
the simplest method possible which kind
of made all of us uh very surprised and
uh kind of uh excited where we focused
on budget forcing where we have a
question like this how many hours are in
raspberry we let the model generate the
response but then if it didn't hit the
allocated token budget we added a token
called weight and then let the model
generate and basically Force the model
generate more in order to response to
that right we're kind of using this
weight token we are hinting the model
that we are not sure if your answer is
correct okay so one more thing to add we
did not train a model to decide when to
add weight we kind of naturally added
weight when it didn't hit our token
budget and then we let the model
generate more until the final answer is
achieved is is obtained okay so now uh
training and results we trained a Quin
32b model uh on this data and here are
our results on the xaxis we are seeing
the the kind of the number of tokens the
average thinking time or the number of
tokens that are generated and then the
accuracy so when we push the model uh to
just generate 512 tokens here is the
accuracy right it's like 65 uh one more
thing if the model gener wants to
generate more tokens than the kind of
than the budget we put end of token
there or end of end of a sentence there
okay so with that we control the
generation so we go from 512 to two uh
20 2048 for Matt 500 data and as you see
over time with more generated tokens we
see this scaling
Trend uh on this math competition data
which is kind of much more challenging
data we even want the model to generate
longer and longer uh Tok uh outcome and
as you see here we see again the same
Trend and also PG level GP QA Diamond
again generating longer and longer
tokens which is which is very
exciting okay um so the zooming in here
are a little bit of how it worked I I
kind of explained it already so when the
model wants to generate more tokens we
we pushed end of sentence to be able to
get these uh kind of shorter
sequences uh and when we want the model
to generate longer like even go beyond
uh 8,000 tokens we push these away token
and force the model to generate
more we compare different types of test
time scaling methods uh here are the
budget forcing uh this kind of steeper
curve uh shows the budget forcing or
sequential scaling we also
did parallel scaling vers via majority
voting where we let the model generate
multiple paths and then kind of do
majority voting or like the
self-consistency check and we saw some
gains but not not that significant right
so this kind of budget forcing uh seemed
much more
successful and much
simpler so here are some of these
ablations that we have done in the model
uh so this is the fin final results on
the left hand side of s1k on all those
three data sets uh comparing with full
collection of data like using
59k uh we see that a little bit higher
numbers uh we get with the full data on
AIM but in other cases pretty much
similar and our s1k data is really high
quality if you you if we just use random
or like just do a bunch of kind of
constraints to find that one 1,000 data
points the results are much much
worse uh we also did a bunch of scaling
ablations when we don't increase any uh
any kind of let the model to train
longer this is the base number so this
is these are the gains that we are
having with this test time scaling if we
replace weight with other tokens like H
alternatively or just let the model
generate without adding any strings we
saw less
gains
okay um so so these are our results for
test time scanning I also want to
highlight two other approaches that we
have been cooking up uh over time and
the idea is and I'm not going to talk
about any details on these next two
methods but the idea is we want to be
very aware and do self-guided generation
at inference time in this work self rag
we build a rag based model retrieval
augmented generation model but in this
setting we trained a language model to
generate tokens but then criticize its
outcomes and self-improve and we did it
total uh the whole loop with generating
these uh critic tokens where the model
generates responses but once in a while
it generates tokens to say if the the
the the generated response makes sense
or not or if the retrieve documents make
sense or not so so these are also very
promising directions in pushing for uh
test time scaling we also showed that
how this uh kind of self-guided
improvement Loop helps in synthesizing
scientific literature and answering very
complex questions about uh scientific
tasks that require lots and lots of
reasoning so please check out these two
papers the the the results are very
interesting we also have a demo which is
op scholar. allen. a where you can play
with this system um type your question
and then see how it can answer and
combine different pieces of information
synthesize knowledge and then answer
queries uh for this type type of
task
okay um this is a demo and I would let
you play with it so I want to very
briefly also talk about uh how reasoning
can get integrated during pre-training
okay so so far what I talked about was
post
trining integrating things at inference
time and now let's kind of go backward
and then say see
uh how these things can be added during
training remember when I said rlr didn't
work when we had weaker base model so we
need to push to have stronger and
stronger base models okay so this is
kind of a when I when we say training
based model it's not just training with
the next token prediction where learning
rate stays the same and so on we usually
do multiple stages of training in this
first stage we have the warmup period
which is which is like which is a very
standard method but then we use cosign
learning rate on to train these models
with the next token prediction on
trillions of tokens okay but then toward
the end of training we curate really
really high quality data in a lot of
cases designed to do more complex
reasoning and then we take the model
that is here the learning rate that is
here and then kind of a nearly to zero
so sometimes this stage is called mid
training uh the role of these 50 billion
tokens is very important because we we
still do next token prediction but these
tokens are very kind of are trying to
focus on very complex tasks uh and
emphasize on more reasoning oriented
setting okay uh and roughly this called
This is called now is pre-training and
then me
training so the pre-training stage it
uses most of the budget in the in the
training stage it uses trillions of
tokens it's pretty much unstructured
diverse text lots of it come from web
data um and we try to use the best type
of data that we could collect given the
compute budget that we have during mid
training it's almost 1% of training the
idea is we're going to upsample high
quality data that we have during
pre-training and then to to make sure
that we have some in domain data but
then we make sure to bring some even
supervised fine-tuning data we bring in
a lot of reasoning type data coding data
uh and we kind of try to emphasize the
quality of the data here okay so this is
for example the pre-training data mix
that we use for all mod 2 uh which are
some of the web page PES some code data
I mean the the leftmost column matters
less the rightmost the categories make
more sense to follow right now our web
pages code data academic papers stem
papers some math web pages and math
proof and so on and in in total we have
roughly four trillion
tokens but then during meid training
stage we started to bring in lots and
lots of math data which started to patch
the math reasoning capabilities that the
model didn't originally have for example
this was very interesting observation we
realize at the end of this stage the MMO
model was not that good in doing
multiplication but much better in doing
addition and subtraction so we started
integrating some multi synthetic
multiplication data uh in the in the mid
training said right so so we kind of you
kind of observe do a lot of kind of
evaluation and then figure out do some
patching to improve the model and then
kind of uh inject that type of knowledge
in the model so as you see in our mid
training mix We included a lot of uh uh
reasoning type
data and then we started evaluating
these models so so this is kind of
evaluating uh our pre-training and
pre-training a and mid trining together
on average we see significant boost in
both setting like from 50 we go to 60
from 56 we go to 68 and the biggest uh
gains are on gsm 8K which is our math
reasoning capabilities and drop which is
also question answering with math data
uh which is which is showing significant
boost there which is very
interesting okay uh so putting all these
together here are ouro two results which
is on par with llama 38v uh we please
refer to the paper uh to look at the
kind of the 13B and most recently we're
going to have a 32b
results okay so with that uh and I want
to finish this that we've seen a lot of
progress in today's AI work uh still we
need a lot of research and innovation in
many newer tasks so here I've listed a
lot of them a lot of them relevant to
reasoning agents language models for
other domain
um and so on which I really would be
excited if I see you work on
that uh with that I want to thank a lot
of people who are in my team in the MMO
and Tulu projects and also my students
at udab uh and a lot of people at AI too
so uh thank you very much also if you
are interested we are hiring uh for all
these projects thank you